Harold Larrabee Papers
Harold Larrabee Papers
1919-1967
Larrabee, Harold A. (Harold Atkins), 1894-1979
1.5 linear ft.
Pamphlets, articles, books, manuscripts, correspondence of the American author and educator.
2712714
Biographical History
Harold Atkins Larrabee (1894-1979) was an American philosopher, author, and teacher.
Born in Melrose, Massachusetts, Larrabee graduated from Harvard University in 1916, received his master's degree from Columbia in 1918 and earned a Ph.D from Harvard in 1925. He taught at Syracuse University and the University of Vermont before joining Union College in Schenectady, New York, where he held the Ichabod Spencer Chair in philosophy until his retirement in 1960. He wrote journal articles, books, pamphlets and book reviews for various outlets, and was for decades the Senior Editor of the New England Quarterly. His writings focused on philosophy, history and the importance of education.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Harold Larrabee Papers consists of correspondence, printed material, and writings.
Correspondence consists of a single folder of letters in response to book reviews written by Larrabee.
Printed material contains articles, essays, books, book reviews, and poems by Larrabee, as well as a few items by others, probably kept by Larrabee as souvenirs or memorabilia.
Writings contains typescripts by Larrabee, many with handwritten corrections, annotations, or revisions. Included are drafts of Larrabee's books Decision on the Chesapeake is here, as well as his thesis and dissertation, "The Philosophical Foundations of the Social Theory of Henri de Saint-Simon."
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically by type of material. Printed material is subdivided by type (articles, books, etc.) and within that alphabetical by title, while writings (manuscripts) are alphabetical by title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Religion and philosophy; Larrabee, Harold A. (Harold Atkins), 1894-1979.; Philosophers -- United States.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Manuscripts for publication.; Philosophers.; Authors.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Harold A. Larrabee, 1967.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Comments on Larrabee's book reviews, 1927; undated; includes letters from author Will Durant, publisher M. Lincoln Schuster (Box 1)
- Printed materials
  - Articles, essays, tributes, etc. by Larrabee, 1927; 1932-1937,; 1942-1945,; 1950-1964,; 1967; 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Book, The Handbook of Political Fallacies, by Jeremy Bentham, 1962; signed and inscribed to SU by Larrabee (Box 1)
  - Book, Reliable Knowledge, by Harold Larrabee, 1945; includes publicity/advertising material from publisher (Box 1)
  - Book reviews, 1933; 1939-1944,; 1953-1955,; 1959,; 1964; includes publicity/advertising material from publisher (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous by others, 1938; 1953,; 1963; Bulletin of the AAUP, memorial tributes to Joseph Rotondo, Union College Symposium program (includes photo of Larrabee) (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Beginning Early, 1919; typescript of article; includes acceptance letter (Box 1)
  - Bibliography of published writings, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Decision on the Chesapeake, undated; typescript; 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Decision on the Chesapeake, 1964; reviews (Box 2)
  - Dissertation, 1925 (Box 2)
  - Dr. Knott's Duel, 1939; typescript; trifold printed version (Box 2)
  - The Philosophical Foundations of the Social Theory of Henri de Saint-Simon, 1925; typescript of thesis, pp. 1-290; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - The Philosophical Foundations of the Social Theory of Henri de Saint-Simon, 1925; typescript of thesis, pp. 291-423; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Reliable Knowledge, Experimental Edition, 1940; mimeographed typescript, bound (Box 3)
  - Reliable Knowledge, Second Experimental Edition, 1941; mimeographed typescript, bound (Box 3)
  - Remarks at the inauguration of T. V. Smith, 1948; typescript draft, heavily corrected and annotated (Box 3)
  - Rhymes about College, 1936; original manuscript as sent to printer, including some pages that are clippings; printed edition (Box 3)
  - The Story of Philosophy by Will and Ariel Durant, review, 1926; typescript draft of Larrabee's review with corrections; reprint of published version (Box 3)
  - What Phliosophy Is, 1928; typescript carbon, with corrections; 2 folders (Box 3)